你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院的新模块
welcome to a new module in pwn college
今天我们要讲的是面向返回编程ROP
today we're going to be talking about return oriented programming
我对这个模块很感兴趣
I'm very excited about this module
ROP是我很关注的话题
ROP is a subject near and dear to my heart
很高兴能传递这些信息给你们
and it'll be great to convey this information to you
希望能让你们和我一样对ROP感到兴奋
and hopefully make you as excited about ROP as I am
好
alright
在我们深入了解什么是ROP之前，快速回顾一下
quick recap before we dive into what is ROP
如果你还记得
if you recall
在整个课程中，你一直在运行shellcode
you've been throughout this course running shellcode
在shellcode模块中，你在各种不同的约束下创建shellcode
in the shellcode module you created shellcode under various different constraints
上传，执行，拿到flag
you upload it you execute it you got the flag
在组合模块（漏洞利用模块）中你结合了
in the combination module you put together
能劫持控制流的内存损坏漏洞和shellcode注入
memory corruption vulnerabilities that led to control flow hijacks with injected shellcode
在大多数情况下，我们假装
and in most cases we pretended that
linux下基于无执行权限位实现的DEP
the mitigation known as data execution prevention implemented via the no execute bit in Linux
它不存在
it did not exist
DEP
data execution prevention of course
阻止你的shellcode在内存中的大多数地方执行
prevents your shellcode from executing in most places in memory
如果你把它放到栈上
if you put it on the stack
然后试着跳到栈
and try to jump to the stack
你的程序只会崩溃
your program will simply crash
因为栈是不可执行的
because the stack is not executable
现在很少有程序有可执行栈
there are very few programs that have an executable stack nowadays
大多数只有
it is mostly not required only real places
在资源有限的特殊嵌入式机器上
outside of exotic embedded situations with small resource constrain machines
可能没有DEP功能
that might not have modern data execution prevention
即便如此，大多数也都支持DEP
even then most things do
shellcode直接能用的唯一地方是
the only place where shellcode directly still relevant is
在及时编译引擎
in just in time compilation engines
你在组合模块（漏洞利用模块）中也利用过了
which you have now in the combination module also exploited
但这些都是视情况的
but those are situational
如果你需要
what if you're looking
能攻破JIT之外系统的方法呢
to break the security of something that is not a just in time compilation system
因此，如果你无法注入代码并执行它
so if you are unable to inject code and execute it
那么我们就转向所谓的代码重用
then we turn to what is called code reuse
这个概念其实很老了
this concept is actually quite old
在32位x86的旧时代
in the old days of 32 bit x86
很久以前
way back when
我记得64位架构已经成为标准超过十年了
I think 64 bit architecture has been the standard for well over a decade now
但在那之前
but before then
在32位x86上，参数是在栈上传递的
on 32 bit x86 arguments were passed on the stack
这有你熟悉的栈帧
so you have your stack frame that might be familiar now
有一个溢出漏洞的缓冲区
you have a vulnerable buffer
有基指针32位x86上叫EBP
you have your saved base pointer EBP on 32 bit x86
有返回地址，然后是
your return address and then
漏洞函数的参数
arguments to the vulnerable function
对，直接就是
right and and this is literally you know
参数1、参数2、参数3等等
arg1 arg2 arg3 and so on
如果是现在的64位system
and just like in modern days
这会放入RDI RSI RDX等等
this would go into RDI on AMD 64 RSI RDX and so on
这就是当时的情况
all right so this is how things worked back then
会将参数压入栈
you would push arguments to the stack
然后调用这个函数
and then you would call the function
这意味着如果有栈溢出
and what this meant is if you had a stack overflow
你能溢出的不仅是返回地址
you could overflow not only the return address
你还能溢出
but you could overflow
你还可以伪造主调（相对被调）栈帧
you could create what is called the call frame
向你重定向到的函数传递参数
create arguments for the code to which you redirected execution
在溢出之前
so before execution
返回地址后面紧跟着就是参数
there would be their return address and arguments immediately
你可以创建umm
next you could would create
你能通过溢出漏洞创建一个
instead with the vulnerability you would create a
例如，你可以将程序重定向到system函数
you'd redirect for example the program to system
当函数返回时，它将跳转到system函数
this would when the vulnerable function return it would jump to system
就好像system被调用了
as if system was just called
所以当然需要一些东西来假装是system函数的返回地址
so of course you need something to pretend to be the return address from system
然后当system找它的参数时
and then when system looked for its argument
它们就在你用溢出控制的栈上
they would be right there on the stack controlled by you because of the stack overflow
这被称为ret2libc
this is called return into libc
用libc中函数的地址覆盖返回地址
you overwrite their return address with an address inside libc
特别是system函数的地址
specifically the address of system
来实现你的目标
to accomplish your goals
它是在90年代中期被一个叫Solar Designer的黑客发现的
it was discovered in the mid 90s by hacker named Solar Designer
这个黑客实际上发现了相当多的利用技术
this hacker actually discovered quite a lot of exploitation techniques
我们将在以后的模块中再次听到他的故事
we will hear about him in a later module again
但在90年代中期
but in the the mid 90s
他声名鹊起的原因之一
one of his claims to fame
就是创造了 ret2libc
was the creation of return to libc
以一个??姿势基本上是在说，嘿，你知道
in a ?? pose that basically said hey look you know
我可以绕过这些流行的DEP
I can bypass this sort of data execution prevention stuff that's coming around
我们在安全防御上还任重道远啊
we need to go beyond that
但那是在32位x86时代
but this was in back in the day in 32 bit x86
32位系统现在不怎么用了
and that is just not what we are running anymore
现代64位架构不通过栈传参数了（对于x86_64少于6个参数的情况）
modern architectures don't take arguments on the stack
在AMD 64中用RDI,RSI等寄存器传递参数
in AMD 64 we have arguments going into RDI RSI etc
所以如果溢出栈
if you overflow the stack
并重定向到system
and redirect execution to system
你无法控制它实际执行的程序
you can't control what it actually executes
好的
right
但事实证明，你仍然可以做一些非常有用的事情
but it turns out there are still very useful things you can do and
事实上你已经做过了
you've already in fact done them
就是在内存错误模块最开始
are taken the 1st steps in the memory errors module
有一个可以重定向到的win函数
there was a win function to which you redirected execution
通过溢出缓冲区并覆盖返回地址来指向win
by overflowing a vulnerable buffer and overwriting the return address to point to win
这是在最开始
this is the beginning
在这种情况下，你不需要传递参数
in this case you didn't need to pass an argument
好的
right
内存错误模块中后续题目里有
there are in later levels of the memory errors module
一个棘手的win函数
we had a tricky win function that would actually
需要传入一个参数1337
you would need to pass in an argument of 1337
否则它会拒绝给你flag
or it would refuse to give you the flag
但
but
很明显你发现了
obviously you figured out that
实际上，如果你完全控制返回地址
actually if you control the return address completely
你可以直接跳过这个检查
you can just jump right past that check part way through the function
现在我们更进了一步，实现高级代码重用
now we're taking  another step to kind of advanced code reuse
你已经重用了函数的一部分
right so you reused part of a function
你可以再进一步
you can go even further
其实你已经做到了
and you have gone further
在组合模块的toddler1习题中执行jit喷射攻击
by performing a jit spray attack in the 1st putting it together module in toddler one
通过跳到一条指令的中间
by jumping partway into an instruction
一条好好的
a nice looking instruction
由前一个模块讲的JIT编译器生成的指令
generated in the case of the previous module by a just in time compiler
但是如果跳转到指令的中间
but if you jump partly into that instruction
指令位于1337000
the instruction is located at 1337 000
然后你跳转到137002
and you jump to 137 002
从这里开始执行
start executing from here
你实际上执行了一些完全不同的指令
you actually execute something very different
在本例中，执行exit系统调用
you execute in this case an exit syscall
这是又一步
so that is yet another step
在这个模块中，我们将学习
and in this module we will learn to take
剩下的步骤最后掌握面向返回编程
the rest of the steps to toward what is known as return oriented programming
ROP是ret2libc的通用泛化
it's a generalization of the technique of return to libc
可以返回到任何地方
it returns to anywhere
它基本上能把你
it basically allows you to take the capabilities
通过溢出栈来得到的能力
that you achieve by overflowing the stack
包括通过返回地址跳转到指令中间
including the return address is being able to jump part way into instructions
跳转到函数中间等
part way into functions etc
一个接一个地链接起来
and chain these returns one after another
来达到你想要达到的漏洞利用效果
to achieve the goals that you want to achieve an exploitation
在这个模块中，你将学习所有这些
in this module you'll learn all about this
你会掌握它
you'll master it
你会真的
and you'll truly
能够破坏一个程序
be able to subvert a program
让它做一些它从来没有被设计过的事情
make it do something that it was absolutely truly never designed to do
只是使用它自己的二进制代码
by using its own binary code against it
让我们看看在模块的其余部分中是什么样子的
let's see what that looks like in the rest of the module